<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>About the Aratea Digital Project</title>
                <author>
                    <persName>
                        <forename>Ivana</forename>
                        <surname>Dobcheva</surname>
                    </persName>
                </author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <publisher/>
                <availability>
                    <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">
                        <p>The (CC BY 4.0)-License applies to this document.</p>
                    </licence>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Born digital.</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>About</head>
                <p> Aratea Digital is a database collecting information about astronomy in the Early
                    Middle Ages. The main focus of the project is the Latin transmission of the
                    so-called Aratea texts including the Latin translations and the derivative texts
                    based on Aratus' didactic poem Phaenomena. The website presents descriptions of
                    their (pre-13th-century) manuscripts, references to the latest editions and
                    relevant literature. </p>
                <p> This website is work-in-progress. We are constantly working on improving and
                    enhancing the information provided. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Goals</head>
                <list>
                    <item>Summary introduction of the Aratea texts, providing basic information on
                        their history, as well as the authoritative edition, relevant literature and
                        links to further resources. Also all manuscripts that contain the respective
                        text will be automatically listed here.</item>
                    <item>
                        <ref target="toc.html?collection=editions">Description</ref> of all pre
                        13th-century manuscripts of the Aratea texts.</item>
                    <item>Indices for all <ref target="places.html">places</ref> and <ref
                        target="persons.html">people</ref> connected with the manuscript
                        transmission of the Aratea, as well as other <ref target="listtitle.html"
                            >text</ref>, which build up their Überlieferungsgemeinschaft. We aim to
                        link all entities with Authority files (<ref
                            target="http://www.dnb.de/DE/Standardisierung/GND/gnd_node.html"
                            >GND</ref> and <ref target="http://www.geonames.org/">geonames</ref>) to
                        facilitate identification and future interoperability.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Manuscripts</head>
                <p> The manuscript descriptions are encoded using the guidelines of the <ref
                    target="http://www.tei-c.org/">Text Encoding Initiative (TEI)</ref>, which
                    is an XML standard widely adopted in the digital humanities for the
                    representation of texts. </p>
                <p> To validate the mark-up we used the TEI P5 schema for <ref
                    target="http://www.europeanaregia.eu/">Europeana Regia</ref> (ER). The
                    practices from the <ref target="http://www.hab.de/">Herzog August library
                        Wolfenbüttel</ref> were taken as an example for structuring the manuscript
                    descriptions. People, places are texts (works within manuscripts) are tagged as
                    such and gathered in indices together with additional information as well as
                    links to further resources. The XML files are also available for download. </p>
                <p> With the growing number of manuscript description being added to the database we
                    are further working on different possibilities to search, filter and analyse the
                    data. Apart from full text search we plan to integrate faceted search to filter
                    the manuscripts according to certain criteria (shelfmark, origin place / time,
                    texts etc.) and possibly to combine different criteria. </p>
                <p><ref target="https://ivanadob.github.io/aratea-data/index-mss.html">Manuscript Descriptions</ref></p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Licence</head>
                <p> The material is licensed under a <ref
                    target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons
                    Attribution 4.0 International license (CC BY 4.0)</ref>, meaning you are
                    free to make use of it, share and adapt it to your need, as long as you give us
                    appropriate credit (mention the project website for instance), provide a link to
                    the license, and indicate if changes were made. </p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
