<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?><?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Huginus: De Astronomia</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition/>
            <respStmt>
               <resp>TEI-P5 coded by</resp>
               <name type="person">
                  <rs type="person" ref="#ivana_dobcheva">Ivana Dobcheva</rs>
               </name>
               <name type="org"/>
            </respStmt>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher></publisher>
            <availability>
               <licence target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY 4.0). You are free to: Share — copy and redistribute the material in any medium or format; Adapt — remix, transform, and build upon the material for any purpose, even commercially. Under the following terms: Attribution — You must give appropriate credit, provide a link to the license, and indicate if changes were made. You may do so in any reasonable manner, but not in any way that suggests the licensor endorses you or your use.</licence>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Information about the source</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>
               <title>Introduction</title>
            </head>            
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>
               <title>Editions</title>
               <listBibl>
                  <bibl>Hyginus. Hygini De Astronomia. Edited by Ghislaine Viré. Bibliotheca Scriptorum Graecorum et Romanorum Teubneriana. Stuttgart: Teubner, 1992.</bibl>
                  <bibl>Hyginus. L’astronomie. Edited by André LeBoeuffle. 2nd ed. Collection Des Universités de France. Paris: Les Belles Lettres, 2002.</bibl>
               </listBibl>
            </head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl>Text online at <ref target="http://latin.packhum.org/loc/899/1/0#0">Classical Latin Texts (The Packard Humanities Institute)</ref></bibl>
               <bibl>Text online at <ref target="http://www.thelatinlibrary.com/hyginus.html">The Latin Library</ref></bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>
               <title>Literature</title>
            </head>
            <listBibl>
               <bibl>Lippincott, Kristen. ‘Exploring Differing Notions of Scholarship in the Eleventh Century: The Two Earliest Extant Illustrated Manuscripts of Hyginus’s “De Astronomia”’. Source: Notes in the History of Art 33, no. 3/4 (2014): 11–18.</bibl>
               <bibl>Viré, Ghislaine. Informatique et Classement Des Manuscrits: Essai Méthodologique Sur Le de Astronomia d’Hygin. Sources et Instruments. Faculté de Philosophie et Lettres. Université Libre de Bruxelles 8. Brussels: Univ. de Bruxelles, 1986.</bibl>
               <bibl>Viré, Ghislaine. La Transmission Du De Astronomia d’Hygin Jusqu’au XIVe Siècle: Informatique et Classement Des Manuscrits. [Université de Bruxelles], 1978.</bibl>
               <bibl>Viré, Ghislaine. ‘Le Texte Du “De Astronomia” d’Hygin: Question de Méthode’. Latomus 51 (1992): 843–56.</bibl>
               <bibl>Viré, Ghislaine. ‘<ref target="https://doi.org/10.3406/antiq.1981.2053">Les extraits du De Astronomia d’Hygin dans les scholies aux Aratea de Cicéron</ref>’. L’Antiquité Classique 50, no. 1 (1981): 801–12.</bibl>
               <bibl>Viré, Ghislaine. ‘<ref target="https://www.persee.fr/doc/ista_0000-0000_1983_ant_273_1_1073">Quelques réflexions sur l’étude d’une tradition manuscrite</ref>’. Collection de l’Institut des Sciences et Techniques de l’Antiquité 273, no. 1 (1983): 249–58.</bibl>
            </listBibl>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>
               <title>Manuscripts</title>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item><ref target="desc__vienna_onb_51.xml">Vienna, Österreichische Nationalbibliothek, Cod. 51</ref></item>
               <item><ref target="desc__bav_reg_lat_1260.xml">Vatican, BAV Reg. lat. 1260</ref> (44v-83v)</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>